<?xml-stylesheet href='resume.xsl' type="text/xsl"?>
<res:resume xmlns:res ="http://aani.ca/resume">
    <general>
        <name>Somar Aani</name>
        <email>aanis@mcmaster.ca</email>
        <linkedin>https://ca.linkedin.com/in/somaraani</linkedin>
    </general>

    <education>
        <institute>
            <name>North Toronto Collegiate Institute</name>
            <degree>Highschool Diploma</degree>
            <graduated>June 2016</graduated>
        </institute>
        <institute>
            <name>McMaster University</name>
            <degree>Bachelor of Engineering (B.Eng.)</degree>
            <graduated>May 2021</graduated>
        </institute>
    </education>

    <work>
        <job>
            <title>Software Development Intern</title>
            <company>IBM</company>
            <start>May 2019</start>
            <end>August 2020</end> 
            <description> Worked on a variety of applications and microservices, 
            including both back-end (Java, Spring, Guice) and front-end (Angular) development, 
            creating and consuming RESTful APIs </description>
            <description> DevOps activities including creating Docker images and 
            deploying to Kubernetes, leveraging Spinnaker, Jenkins, Travis and Ansible 
            scripts for automating deployment of large scale applications and services </description>
            <description> Created API performance, functional and stress tests using JMeter, RESTAssured, and Gatling  </description>
        </job>

        <job>
            <title>Mobile Development Intern</title>
            <company>Checkout51</company>
            <start>May 2018</start>
            <end>August 2018</end> 
            <description> Developed a standalone automation utility and custom testing framework 
            from the ground-up, that is cross-platform for both iOS and Android, with an easy 
            to use GUI that allows dynamic creation of test suites. Was implemented 
            into the QA process, with plans to expand test range using the framework. </description>
            <description> Refactored a major component for the Checkout51 iOS app from Objective-C to Swift, 
            as well as upgrading the architecture with a focus on improving maintainability and performance </description>
            <description> Was assigned JIRA tickets as part of the release cycle for fixing bugs and implementing new 
            features using Android Studio and Kotlin/Java, including version control (git), code review and testing  </description>
        </job>

        <job>
            <title>Application Programmer Analyst </title>
            <company>Ontario Ministry of Education</company>
            <start>May 2017</start>
            <end>August 2017</end> 
            <description> Developed internal testing utilities using C# and .NET for parsing and 
            validating huge PDF reports. These were implemented into the QA process, 
            largely improving efficiency from the old manual process. </description>
            <description> Referenced business and technical documentation to create
             full-coverage tests for both functional and GUI testing, including both 
             new features and regression tests </description>
            <description> Developed libraries to improve automation tasks, including reporting 
            libraries and maintaining a data driven testing framework  </description>
        </job>
    </work>
</res:resume>